I've got updates on the tiny brains if
you are not familiar with brain
organoids they are tiny human brains
that we can grow from stem cells you can
grow them in a literal jar if you want
to but you can also hook them up to a
computer or llm since a company called
final spark decided to release brain
organoid computation for industrial use
there has been an explosion in research
in figuring out how to make them better
processors and yes those are real eyes
granted they are ocular cups similar to
what you would see in a fetus we'll talk
about it all of it as far as we know the
first brain organoids were grown out of
lab in Kyoto in 2008 since then everyone
has been trying to put them on a
computer chip and it has progressed
significantly in 2022 a company called
cortical Labs announced to the world
that they believed the brain organoids
were sentient this was based on the fact
that they could hook them up to a
computer chip and they could learn how
to play Pong now sentience is the
ability to have a sensation and then
react to it not only did the brain
organoids demonstrate that they could
learn but they're also capable of
sensation rather they're capable of
having a feeling and then responding to
that feeling in the case of the early
brain organoid computation it was based
on ordered and disordered signals they
could send signals to them and receive
what came back they could receive that
information and use it they were capable
of learning to play Pong faster and
better than AI systems just 3 years ago
now final spark took it to a whole new
level they found out you could train the
brains on dopamine so when they made
electrical output that would trigger a
machine to give them a little jolt of it
in that way they became addicted to
actually solving our problems for us and
doing computation along with cortical
labs they also embodied them in a game
World they gave it a virtual body in
this case multiple brain organoids ran a
butterfly simulation that simulation is
not up right now but I have made a video
on it there has been a lot of
limitations to not just growing them but
being able to keep them alive and
running a computer system because they
are disembodied they lack a circulatory
system and they're developing
independently of a skull they would
normally develop in as a result our
little friends end up dying of hypoxia
although there has been a lot of
research now in keeping them alive for
longer using a gel diffusion system
where media has constantly cycled out
they've managed to keep them alive for a
year or more as they develop they do
look very much like a fetal human brain
although teeny tiny we're talking
micrometers here and yes the longer that
they are kept alive the more that their
gene expression and brain waves resemble
a premature baby but do remember just
because we're talking about something
that may resemble that brain on test
we're talking about something that is
like a thousand micrometers across I
feel like I'm ethically required to tell
you guys that they're not conscious
until they can demonstrate the abstract
concept of self when I've talked to
researchers about this they can't help
but mentioned to me that no they're not
comparable to a baby although babies are
also not conscious they only have Delta
brain waves until around the time
they're naturally born so premature
babies essentially have the brain waves
of a c patient and assuming all goes
well they'll eventually develop to where
they should be researchers generally
think this is really freaking cool but
it tends to creep everyone out I'd like
to remind you yes those are eyes the
most effective way of keeping a brain
organoid alive and is also one of the
things that I would love to see more of
is using them to treat stroke patients
there has been a good deal of success
with treating simulated Strokes in mice
with human brain organoids being
transplanted they grow they will
integrate and there's even been some
research using them in monkeys damaged
monkey brain tiny human brain put in
there to repair a stroke this would be
an amazing treatment in humans but it is
again the most effective way to keep one
Alive Now final spark yes the company
that is selling these guys computation
as a subscription model for $500 a month
also partnered with a number of labs
around the world to research different
aspects of the use of human brain
organoids in computation and we are just
starting to see the products of that
this lab came out of University of
California and Kyoto and they managed to
figure out how to take a complex human
brain organoid and put it into a
computer if you look back at this
picture you may notice a few things it's
really small it's relatively flat and it
doesn't have the complex sprin
structures that we can see in other
brain organoids well you can grow
multiple structures in the same brain
organoid it's kind of difficult without
you know the whole body to grow it in
one possible solution is to grow
separate parts and assemble them and I'm
slightly entertained that this research
group called them legol like bricks this
is great if you're doing medical
research trying to figure out how say
drugs would affect the brain not the
greatest thing to use if you're trying
to make it into a computation model
getting it oxygen and keeping it alive
is a lot more complicated if it's more
complex so they usually only use one
kind of brain tissue there's also the
issue of communicating with it well yes
you can train it on things like dopamine
or ordered or disordered signals that's
not very helpful if you have to receive
that information and you've got a
three-dimensional structure I've seen
some research groups that grow them in
Cami baskets so they have some
three-dimensional interactions with the
organoid still it's difficult to work
with this group decided to create a
three-dimensional little box to store a
brain organoid in and they have multiple
outputs and input so they can
communicate with the entire brain
structure this would allow them to have
increasingly complex brain organoids to
work with as the technology develops
we'll probably develop better way to get
them oxygen than diffusion I have seen
quite a lot of work with vascularizing
them using vascular organoids still
lacks a heart and we need to do
something like ECMO and we know that
eemo is very hard on little human brains
if perfected I wonder if we couldn't end
up one day with something that is more
complicated than a human brain already
human brains are the best in the
business better than any computer that
we have they're made even be Quantum
Dynamics going on in our brains it is
kind of cool that we conscious pieces of
the universe are trying to understand
ourselves and now we are trying to
recreate ourselves in peace meal the one
thing you should be asking yourself is
what about the ethics of it this is an
completely new field I don't think
anyone ever considered ethics of how we
would get here we have rules for human
experimentation we have rules for
Animals we do not have rules for
disembodied human organs grown in a lab
I think we'll get one of three maybe
four outcomes to This research one it'll
be so good it'll be integrated
everywhere we might find that people
don't actually want to feed their
computers fish flakes and it might just
not be worth it it might just be easier
to make quantum computers than try to
integrate human brains third option is
maybe we'll all decide that this was a
horribly unethical idea and we never
should have done it and it'll be seen as
a horror of scientific history like many
things have become perhaps the most
unlikely result is that they'll end up
gaining Consciousness and work with AI
to take over the world and destroy us
all I think that is highly unlikely but
anything's possible in addition to being
a researcher myself granted I don't work
with this stuff I work as soil I do find
this stuff really fascinating extremely
creepy but I love sci-fi and I love
horror and I think I've been in a little
bit of disbelief that this actually
managed to happen what do you
think than the tiny Pro carots swarming
in the culture